<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yachting.earth/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://yachting.earth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-19T10:46:48+02:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Yachting.Earth</title><subtitle>!J.A.Y.S.</subtitle><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><entry><title type="html">2024</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2024/03/06/2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2024" /><published>2024-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-03-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2024/03/06/2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2024/03/06/2024.html"><![CDATA[<p>Vår plan för 2024 är äntligen klar, efter många turer fram och tillbaks är vi äntligen klara. I alla fall med de stora dragen, de mindre tar vi som det kommer. :)</p>

<p>Vill du ha koll så hittar du planen här –&gt; <a href="/2024">planen för 2024</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Fix" /><category term="Freya" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vår plan för 2024 är äntligen klar, efter många turer fram och tillbaks är vi äntligen klara. I alla fall med de stora dragen, de mindre tar vi som det kommer. :)]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/2024-a.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/2024-a.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Vår nya favoritrom</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2024/02/07/Var-nya-favorit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vår nya favoritrom" /><published>2024-02-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2024/02/07/Var-nya-favorit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2024/02/07/Var-nya-favorit.html"><![CDATA[<p>Fick smaka en ny rom* hos grannbåten, Don Papa Baroko. Lite otippat hörde den hemma på ön Negros på Filippinerna. Då ön mer eller mindre skapades av en vulkan en gång i tiden så är sockerrören rommen är gjord av extra söta.</p>

<p><img src="negros.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Rommen* som är lagrad i 3 år är söt med massor av smak av vanilj, honung, citrus och torkade frukter och massa kryddor. Nästan lite söt efterrätt över det hela.</p>

<p>Den skarpsynta har säkert noterat den lilla asterisken bakom <em>Rom</em> ovan, den är där för att en tjänsteman vid EU-parlamentet vid något tillfälle inte tyckte att en rom får ha mer än 20 gram tillsatt socker i EU. Det gjorde att Don Papa fick göra en liten rockad i sitt sortiment så den tidigare rommen Don Papa fick byta namn till Don Papa Barocko samtidigt som den klassades om till “lagrad sockerrörssprit” för att göra alla glada. Sockerhalten ligger fortfarande på 30 gram/liter och den tidigare och alla är glada.</p>

<p>Men mest glada är vi för vi har hittat en ny favorit oavsett vad den kallas.</p>

<p>Flaskan hittar man i Sverige på <a href="https://www.systembolaget.se/produkt/sprit/don-papa-5319301/">Systembolaget</a> där den inte är vidare dyr (strax över 400kr), utanför Sverige beställs den via Amazon för €33kr.</p>

<p><img src="don-papa-baroko.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="mat" /><category term="dryck" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fick smaka en ny rom* hos grannbåten, Don Papa Baroko. Lite otippat hörde den hemma på ön Negros på Filippinerna. Då ön mer eller mindre skapades av en vulkan en gång i tiden så är sockerrören rommen är gjord av extra söta.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/don-papa-baroko.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/don-papa-baroko.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Volvo, Volvo, kära oljeläckande Volvo!</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/05/29/volvo-volvo-kara-oljelackande-volvo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Volvo, Volvo, kära oljeläckande Volvo!" /><published>2023-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/05/29/volvo-volvo-kara-oljelackande-volvo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/05/29/volvo-volvo-kara-oljelackande-volvo.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ombord Freya tycker vi inte om att använda motorn mer än nödvändigt hon är ju trots allt en segelbåt och sådana ska seglas men ibland får man inte som man vill och då är det skönt att ha en motor som fungerar och som är i ordning.</p>

<p>Motorn i Freya är en nästan ny (några hundra timmar gammal) Volvo Penta D2-75, för er som inte är så bevandrade inom marina motorer så är det en 75 hästars rak, färskvattenkyld, 4 cylindrig motor med insprutning och turbo. D2-75 är en helt okey motor även om jag personligen gärna hade varit utan turbo vilket den här texten kommer handla om.</p>

<p>Det där med att ha en motor som fungerar och är i ordning betyder att järnklumpen kräver både regelbunden tillsyn och service med allt vad det betyder.</p>

<p>Om du är ägare till en Volvo Penta D2-75’a så är det nu det intressanta börjar och skulle det vara så att du inte äger en båtmotor med turbo och intercooler så är jag säker på att resterande text kommer vara urtrist så varför inte läsa lite om gott bröd här istället » Kaptenen bakar</p>

<p>Ah, du är fortfarande kvar. Vid tillsynen hittade vi olja på bälgen till S-drevet, det var inte några mängder men det var på tok för mycket för att kunna avskrivas som spill vid service så det var tvunget att komma från motorn på ett eller annat vis.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="image-7.png" /></td>
      <td><img src="image.png" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Malö 116, båten vi seglar, har ett hyfsat stort motorrum men då D2-75 är en hyfsat stor motor betyder det att så fort något ska göras med motorn är det som att jobba i en byrålåda passande i ett mindre dockhus. Efter att monterat bort luftburken gick det klämma in en arm bakom motorn för att känna efter mer olja och med telefonens kamera knipa några bilder varav nedanstående är en av dem.</p>

<p><img src="image-1.png" /></p>

<p>Den skarpsynte ser genast spåren av olja på ovansidan av svänghjulskåpan vilket i sann Sherlock Holmes andra betyder att det är något längre upp som läcker olja. På just Volvo Penta D2-75 sitter turbo och intercooler på baksidan av motorn, strax över svänghjulskåpan…</p>

<p>Då jag inte hade en blekaste aning om hur de tidigare ägarna kört motorn samtidigt som jag var ganska säker på att de förlitat sig helt och håller på auktoriserade Volvo Penta verkstäder (de hade ju fortfarande garanti på motorn) med allt var det betyder kunde jag inte vara säker på att turbo och avgasknä (där avgaserna blandas med kylvatten) inte var igensatt med koks från att gått på för låga varv så det blev kort och gott till att demontera kalaset då varken turbons eller avgasknäts insida ingår i den auktoriserade servicen. Tur nog satt det hela bara med en handfull bultar så svordomarna blev inte så många som väntat.</p>

<p><img src="image-2.png" /></p>

<p>Turbon såg inte så illa ut, det enda var dumpventilen som gick lite väl trögt pga sotet. Efter en snabb rengöring så såg den både ut och fungerade som när den var ny.</p>

<p><strong>OBS! Om du som läser det här funderar på att rengöra din turbo var lika försiktig med turbons fläktblad som du skulle vara om du byggde korthus eller desarmerade en bomb. De är känsliga med massor av precision (de snurrar mellan 60000 och 300000 varv per minut beroende på motor) vilket gör den dyr!!</strong></p>

<p>Värre var det med avgasknät, den var igenmurad av koks och elände vilket är ganska vanligt på den här modellen av avgasknä då inloppet till kylvattnet kommer lite för tidigt så att avgaserna kyls ner för effektivt vilket i sin tur skapar lite oreda och service behov. Det finns “kopior” i rostfritt där den som designat knät tänkt till som inte slår igen på något år och att de är rostfria får man på köpet. 🙂</p>

<p><img src="avgaskrok-rotated.jpg" /></p>
<center>På bilden ovan har en del av koksen redan pillats bort.</center>

<p>Aningens förbryllande då varken sotet i turbon eller den något igensatta knät kunde vara orsak till oljan så det enda som återstod att kontrollera var intercoolern som sitter mellan turbo och motorn.</p>

<p>Vi närmar oss nu problemet och för att förstå varför saker ser ut som det gör behöver vi känna till lite om hur en turbo och en intercooler fungerar.</p>

<p>Turbon har som primär uppgift att trycka in mer syre i motorn än vad den klara av att suga i sig på egen hand, dvs turbon komprimerar luft (ökar dess densitet) så att mer syre kommer in och kan förbrännas i motorn. Detta är såklart bra för motorn prestanda men vad som inte är så bra är att turbon även tillför massa värme till luften/syret som ska förbrännas både för att den är hiskligt varm i sig själv (turbo drivs av motorns avgaser) och på grund av att när luft komprimeras rör sig molekylerna snabbare vilket i sin tur ökar temperaturen (kompressionsvärme) och värme gör att luften expanderar vilket är lite kontra produktivt i det hela. För att stilla den inre nörden så är energin som frigörs lika stor som energin som går åt till att komprimera luften.</p>

<p>Så för att lösa det hela med för varm luft stoppar tillverkarna in en intercooler vars uppgift är att kyla ner den av turbon komprimerade luften för att öka dess densitet, vilket i sin tur gör att mer syre kan pressas in motorn per cykel i förbränningen. Det i sin tur gör att motorn blir effektivare och kan leverera mer mer effekt (hästkrafter).</p>

<p>Problemet med att öka densiteten på vanlig luft är att den alltid innehåller en del fukt och den fukten komma bilda kondens på kylflänsarna i intercoolern och för att bli av med kondensen har Volvo, eller vem det nu är som designat intercoolern, helt enkelt valt att borra ett litet hål i botten av intercoolern och låta kondensen droppa ner och helt enkelt blåsas ut från motorn av turbons tyck.</p>

<p><img src="intercooler.jpg" /></p>

<p>I det stora hela är det en smart och enkel lösning <strong>MEN</strong> det är inte bara luft som kommer in i intercoolern utan även en liten liten mängd olja som sugs/tryck ut från turbons små lager. Den oljan hamnar precis som kondensen i botten på intercoolern men istället för att blåsas ut och avdunsta i motorrummet så rinner den sakta ner längs baksidan på motorn och skitar ner allt i sin väg.</p>

<p>Det är nu man ställer sig frågan; “Hur svårt och dyrt skulle det vara för Volvo att koppla på en liten slang och leda olja till ett kärl istället för att trycka ut den i motorrummet?”</p>

<p>Eftersom du läst såhär långt anar jag att du är lite intresserad av en lösning och den kommer i form av en 19,90kr bollpumpsnål från » <a href="https://www.biltema.se/fritid/sport/fotboll/fotbollar/nalar-till-bollpump-2000034188">Biltema</a> eller liknande varuhus.</p>

<p><img src="image-4.png" /></p>

<p>Såga av nålen så att den inte sticker ut på insidan av intercoolern, fäst den med lämpligt klet (silikon, packningsmassa eller något annat som tål värme och tätar), koppla på en slang och dra den till en flaska som monteras där du lätt kommer åt. Jag drog slangen till framsidan av motorn så ser jag flaskan var gång jag öppnar till motorn.</p>

<p><img src="image-5.png" /></p>

<p>Lite drygt 150 timmar senare har flaskan samlat upp i runda slängar 1 dl olja som annars skulle hamnat i motorrummet. Det enda tråkiga är att det är mer eller mindre omöjligt att montera nålen och slangen utan att demontera intercoolern men det positiva är att det inte krävs några speciella verktyg och att det bara tar en halv dag (inklusive fika) att göra det.</p>

<p>I det stora hela är D2-75 en finfin motor om den hanteras som det är tänk, den är inte tänkt att gå på låga varv i dagar i sträck den ska inte heller användas för att ladda batterier på tomgång mer än nödvändigt. Det går såklart men se till att bränna ur den ordentligt relativt regelbundet, vi gör det mer eller mindre var gång vi använder motorn. Med bränna ur menar jag massor av varv (max eller nära på) i 10-15 minuter beroende på hur länge vi kört och på vilket varvtal.</p>

<p><strong>Bonus 1!</strong></p>

<p>Enligt manualen (sidan 52, den har du läst eller hur?!) så ska turbons dumpventil motioneras en aning när motorn inte används på länge. Det gör man genom att vrida den fram och tillbaks max 15 grader med med en fast nyckel. Problemet här är att den som designade avgaskröken inte pratat med den som designade turbon så på avgaskröken sitter där en liten klack som hindrar dumpventilen från att öppna mer än några grader. Så när du ändå har avgaskröken borta kan du lika gärna passa på och slipa ner den där klacken lite så att dumpventilen går att motionera enligt manualen.</p>

<p><img src="image-6.png" /></p>

<p><strong>Bonus 2:</strong></p>

<p>Om du som läser den här texten skulle råka vara ägare till en D2-75’a så kan det vara bra att känna till att motorn är mer eller mindre en vanlig Perkins 404 och den i sin tur är en Shibaura N844L, de 2 sistnämnda används flitigt i traktorer. Nu passar såklart alla delar inte då D2-75’an har konverterats till marint bruk när det kommer till kylsystemet men oljefilter, turbo och många andra delar är exakt samma som “Volvo original” vilket betyder att det finns ganska mycket pengar att spara på att använda originaldelarna från Perkins eller Shibaura istället för de som Volvo slängt på sin logo och höjt priset på med 500%.</p>

<hr />

<p>Volvo, Volvo, dear “oil-leaking” Volvo!
On board Freya, we don’t like to use the engine more than necessary. After all, she is a sailboat, and such boats are meant to be sailed. But sometimes we don’t get what we want, and then it’s nice to have a functioning engine that is in good condition.</p>

<p>The engine in Freya is nearly new (a few hundred hours old) Volvo Penta D2-75. For those who are not well-versed in marine engines, it is a 75-horsepower, straight, freshwater-cooled, 4-cylinder engine with injection and turbo. The D2-75 is a decent engine, although personally, I would have preferred it without a turbo, which is the topic of this text.</p>

<p>Having a functioning and well-maintained engine means that the iron lump requires regular inspection and service, with all that it entails.</p>

<p>If you are the owner of a Volvo Penta D2-75, this is where it gets interesting. And if you don’t own a boat engine with a turbo and an intercooler, I’m sure the rest of the text will be extremely boring. So why not read about good bread here instead » Captain Bakes.</p>

<p>Ah, you’re still here. During the inspection, we found oil on the bellows of the stern drive. It wasn’t a large amount, but it was far too much to be dismissed as spillage during service, so it had to come from the engine in one way or another.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="image-7.png" /></td>
      <td><img src="image.png" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Malö 116, the boat we sail, has a fairly large engine room, but since the D2-75 is a fairly large engine, it means that whenever something needs to be done with the engine, it feels like working in a drawer fitting in a smaller dollhouse. After removing the air filter housing, I managed to squeeze my arm behind the engine to check for more oil and took a few pictures with the phone’s camera, one of which is shown below.</p>

<p><img src="image-1.png" /></p>

<p>The keen-eyed immediately spots the traces of oil on the top of the flywheel housing, which, in true Sherlock Holmes fashion, means that there is a leak higher up. On the Volvo Penta D2-75 specifically, the turbo and intercooler are located at the back of the engine, just above the flywheel housing…</p>

<p>Since I had no clue about how the previous owners had driven the engine, while being fairly certain that they relied entirely on authorized Volvo Penta workshops (after all, they still had a warranty on the engine), I couldn’t be sure that the turbo and exhaust manifold weren’t clogged with carbon deposits from running at too low RPMs. So, in short, it came down to dismantling it. Fortunately, it was held together with just a handful of bolts, so the curses weren’t as numerous as expected.</p>

<p><img src="image-2.png" /></p>

<p>The turbo didn’t look too bad, the only issue was the waste gate, which was a bit sluggish due to the soot. After a quick cleaning, it looked like new.</p>

<p>NOTE! If you are planning to clean your turbo, be as careful with the blades of turbofan as you would be if you were building a house of cards or disarming a bomb. They are delicate and expensive!</p>

<p>The exhaust manifold was worse; it was clogged with carbon buildup, which is quite common in this model of exhaust manifold because the coolant inlet comes a little too early, causing the exhaust gases to cool down too efficiently, resulting in some disorder and the need for servicing. There are “copies” available in stainless steel where the designer of the manifold has thought ahead, ensuring they won’t clog for years, and the fact that they are stainless steel is an added benefit. 🙂</p>

<p><img src="avgaskrok-rotated.jpg" /></p>
<center>In the picture above, a some of the carbon buildup has already been removed.</center>

<p>Slightly perplexing since neither the soot in the turbo nor the somewhat clogged exhaust pipe could be the cause of the oil, so the only thing left to check was the intercooler located between the turbo and the engine.</p>

<p>We are now getting closer to the problem, and in order to understand why things look the way they do, we need to know a little about how a turbo and an intercooler work.</p>

<p>The primary task of the turbo is to force more air into the engine than it can naturally intake on its own. In other words, the turbo compresses the air (increases its density) so that more oxygen enters and can be burned in the engine. This is, of course, beneficial for the engine’s performance. However, what is not so good is that the turbo also adds a lot of heat to the air/oxygen that will be burned, both because it is extremely hot itself (the turbo is driven by the engine’s exhaust gases) and because when air is compressed, the molecules move faster, which in turn increases the temperature (heat of compression). To satisfy the inner nerd, the energy released is equal to the energy required to compress the air.</p>

<p>The intercooler’s task is to cool down the air that has been compressed by the turbo in order to increase its density, which in turn allows more oxygen to be squeezed into the engine per combustion cycle. This, in turn, makes the engine more efficient and capable of delivering more power (horsepower).</p>

<p>The problem with increasing the density of regular air is that it always contains some moisture and that moisture can form condensation on the fins of the intercooler. To get rid of the condensation, Volvo, or whoever designed the intercooler, simply chose to drill a small hole in the bottom of the intercooler and let the condensation drip down and be blown out of the engine by the turbo’s force.</p>

<p><img src="intercooler.jpg" /></p>

<p>Overall, it’s a smart and simple solution, BUT it’s not just air that enters the intercooler, there’s also a small amount of oil that is sucked/pressed from the small bearings in the turbo. That oil ends up, just like the condensation, at the bottom of the intercooler, but instead of evaporating after being blown out in the engine compartment, it slowly drips down the back of the engine, making a mess of everything in its way.</p>

<p>So the question is; ‘How difficult and expensive would it be for Volvo to connect a small hose and direct the oil into a container instead of pushing it out into the engine compartment?’</p>

<p>Since you’ve read this far, I suspect you’re somewhat interested in a solution, and it comes in the form of a 19.90 SEK ball pump needle from » <a href="https://www.biltema.se/fritid/sport/fotboll/fotbollar/nalar-till-bollpump-2000034188">Biltema</a> or a similar department store.</p>

<p><img src="image-4.png" /></p>

<p>Cut off the needle so that it doesn’t stick out on the inside of the intercooler, secure it with a suitable adhesive (silicone, gasket compound, or something else that can withstand heat and seal), attach a hose, and run it to a bottle that is mounted where you can easily access it. I ran the hose to the front of the engine so that I see the bottle every time I open the engine cover.</p>

<p><img src="image-5.png" /></p>

<p>About 150 hours later, the bottle collected roughly 1 dl of oil that would otherwise have ended up in the engine compartment. The only downside is that it’s more or less impossible to install the needle and hose without disassembling the intercooler. However, the positive side is that no special tools are required, and it only takes half a day (including breaks) to do it.</p>

<p>All in all, the D2-75 is a great engine if handled as intended. It’s not meant to run at low speeds for days on end, nor should it be used to charge batteries at idle more than necessary. Of course, it’s possible, but make sure to properly burn it out relatively regularly. We do it almost every time we use the engine. By burning it out, I mean revving it up (close to the maximum) for 10-15 minutes, depending on how long we’ve been running and at what RPM.</p>

<p><strong>Bonus 1!</strong></p>

<p>According to the manual (page 52, you have read it haven’t you?), the turbo’s dump valve should be exercised a bit when the engine is not used for a long time. This is done by turning it back and forth a maximum of 15 degrees using a wrench. The problem here is that the person who designed the exhaust manifold didn’t talk to the person who designed the turbo, so there’s a small tab on the exhaust manifold that prevents the blow-off valve from opening more than a few degrees. So while you have the exhaust manifold off, you might as well take the opportunity to file down that tab a bit, allowing the blow-off valve to be exercised according to the manual.</p>

<p><img src="image-6.png" /></p>

<p><strong>Bonus 2:</strong></p>

<p>If you happen to be the owner of a D2-75, it may be good to know that the engine is more or less a regular Perkins 404, which in turn is a Shibaura N844L. The last two mentioned engines are commonly used in tractors. Of course, not all parts fit perfectly since the D2-75 has been converted for marine use when it comes to the cooling system. However, the oil filter, turbo, and many other parts are exactly the same as “Volvo original,” which means that there is quite a lot of money to save by using the original parts from Perkins or Shibaura instead of those Volvo branded and priced with a 500% markup.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Fix" /><category term="Freya" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ombord Freya tycker vi inte om att använda motorn mer än nödvändigt hon är ju trots allt en segelbåt och sådana ska seglas men ibland får man inte som man vill och då är det skönt att ha en motor som fungerar och som är i ordning.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/image-7.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/image-7.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lite kökspyssel</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/23/Kokspyssel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lite kökspyssel" /><published>2023-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/23/Kokspyssel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/23/Kokspyssel.html"><![CDATA[<p>Vi har länge funderat på att piffa till köket i Freya då det sett sina bästa dagar, det kanske inte ser så illa ut i sig men då man bor ombord på heltid kan det bli lite mörkt och trist när det första man ser när man kommer ombord är ett pentry i mahogny.</p>

<p><img src="pentry_old-450x600.jpg" /></p>
<center>Pentry Freya 1984 – 2023</center>

<p>Så sagt och gjort började vi leta efter lämpliga lösningar och efter att ha funderat på allt från kofot till ny båt kom vi fram till att laminatskivor från Formica skulle kunna göra susen. Vi beställde en handfull med provbitar och efter en del övervägande kom vi fram till att Virrvar kunde vara trevligt, tyvärr var just det mönstret slut hos leverantören så vi beställde Polarvit som var alternativ två på listan.</p>

<p>Efter många mail fram och tillbaks med Formicas återförsäljare på Sicilien som inte kunde mer än “Hello” på engelska slutade det hela med att vi, på italienska, lyckades beställa tre vita skivor (de ska även räcka till att piffa toaletten/badrummet) för 160€ + 50€ i frakt som efter någon vecka låg så fint i båten och tog plats.</p>

<p><img src="formica-600x450.jpg" /></p>
<center>Rullade Formica skivor</center>

<p>Då den tidigare yrkesrollen inte var möbelsnickare var det en hel del funderingar på lämpliga sätt att både få gigantiska laminatskivor att bli mindre och i rätt form i en hyfsat liten båt och inte nog med det hur tusan de senare monteras? Efter en drös med tester med bågfilsblad, sticksåg med och utan tejpade laminatkanter så landade valet på en liten batteridriven vinkelslip med diamantklinga. Den skar laminatet som smör utan att flisa kanterna. Jag hade gärna kapat laminatet utanför på bryggan men kombinationen av lite för mycket vind och stora otympliga skivor gjorde att jag valde att damma ner skutan istället. Var inte alls sugen på att kitesurfa i marinan och vi har ju trotts allt damsugare ombord så det fick bli att damma “lite” &lt;— Lite är en underdrift med råge….</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CvqSDX3j8O0?si=_ah6ccohQXs5IlK_" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>För fastsättning valdes Biltemas Multibond (inte Multibond Rapid!) som inte hugger direkt men i stort sett biter på allt som finns. Testade med att både lägga strängar på ett par brädbitar och trycka dit ett par beställda provbitar av laminatet med gummiroller och att spackla ut limmet i olika tjocklekar. Det som passade bäst på Freya var att spackla ut limmet tunnt, det bet precis lika bra som ett tjockt lager lim fast det gick åt betydligt mindre. Efter limmet torkat testades att skada laminatet med både tappade knivar, kastruller och ett och annat hammarslag utan framgång vilket få ses som en vinst i val av laminat och metod. Ett tips är att beställa ett gäng olika provbitar från Formica även om de inte behövs för att välja laminat, de är perfekta att testa att såga, limma, böja, skruva eller slagtesta ytan på utan att behöva använda den “riktiga” skivan.</p>

<p><img src="test1-225x300.jpg" /> | <img src="test1.1-225x300.jpg" /></p>
<center>Test av lim</center>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kMSIpj_KKXI?si=CPYt_4R3npPp4A9x" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Eftersom den nya vasken var något mindre än den tidigare då vi valt att gå mot en något större enkelho för att kunna diska större grytor och ungspannor istället för två mindre som den gamla fick det gamla hålet byggas igen en aning innan ytan kunde ruggas upp, spacklas och slipas inför limmandet av laminatet.</p>

<p><img src="diskbank-768x1024.jpg" /></p>
<center>Justering av bänk</center>

<p>Efter att bänken var snickrad sågad och klar var det bara att rulla ut papp och rita mallen, tydligen är laminat lite besvärligt att lappa så man bara får en chans att såga. Planen var att kapa så lite som möjligt och göra skivan nåååågot större än vad bänken där det går för att använda en överhandsfräs till att fixa till kanterna.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="mall-225x300.jpg" /></td>
      <td><img src="laminatmall-225x300.jpg" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><img src="diskbank-768x1024.jpg" /></p>
<center>Det tar sig</center>

<p>Efter att det tillkapade laminatet passats in är det bara lite lim som saknas sen börjar det likna ett kök igen. Hela ytan spacklades med lim, ut mot kanterna var det extra noga för att att säkerställa vidhäftning. Ska vara ärlig och säga att ett visst stresspåslag dök upp när limmet spacklades på även om tidigare test visat att det var gott om tid innan det började torka. Det märktes framför allt på slutet då det blev lite mycket lim på sina ställen. När skivan hamnade på sin plats var det enkelt att efterjustera den så att alla kanter hamnade där de skulle innan den trycktes på plats ordentligt och rollades för att jämna ut och säkerställa anläggningen mot limmet under.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="lim-225x300.jpg" /></td>
      <td><img src="limmatlaminat-225x300.jpg" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>På tok för mycket lim men det blev bra ändå när laminatet kom på plats
Efter att laminatet kom på plats var det bara att installera den nya kranen, vasken och laminera luckan till kylen och täckskivan till spisen så var det hela klart. Det hela tog nog en vecka med några timmars faktiskt jobb var dag och massor av funderande på hur saker skulle göras för att bli så bra som möjligt. Självklart finns det säkert betydligt smartare och bättre sätt att göra det hela på men i det stora hela blev det hela helt ok.</p>

<p><img src="efter-2048x1536.jpg" /></p>
<center>Pentry Freya 2023 –</center>

<p>Prislappen på det hela landade på ca 250€ vilket i skrivandets stund är ca 2800kr vilket få ses som en helt ok investering för att få ett “nytt” kök.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Laminatskiva 50€</li>
  <li>Ny vask 119€</li>
  <li>Ny kran 70€</li>
  <li>Lim 5€</li>
</ul>

<p>Verktygen som användes utan inbördes ordning var:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Vinkelslip med diamantklinga</li>
  <li>Överhandsfräs</li>
  <li>Kofot</li>
  <li>Spackelspade</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Fix" /><category term="Freya" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vi har länge funderat på att piffa till köket i Freya då det sett sina bästa dagar, det kanske inte ser så illa ut i sig men då man bor ombord på heltid kan det bli lite mörkt och trist när det första man ser när man kommer ombord är ett pentry i mahogny.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/efter-2048x1536.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/efter-2048x1536.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Polarsteps</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/22/Polarsteps.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polarsteps" /><published>2023-01-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/22/Polarsteps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/22/Polarsteps.html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, let’s begin with the update… Since we (mainly Tony) are lazy, like crazy lazy, when it comes to writing an executive decision has been made in the social media department of Freya and that is that future blog posts will be written in Swedish instead of English. The main reason for that is that most of our “followers” (read friends and family) are Swedish and quite a few of them aren’t that savvy when it comes to reading and understanding English. However, we will still use English when we share stuff on Instagram, Facebook and other social media platforms aaaand the technical department will do its best to include some half-decent translation service for you. Sorry for any inconvenience but life isn’t fair. 😉</p>

<p>Talking about social platforms we recently got introduced to Polarsteps by a friendly neighbour. Polarsteps is kind of a photobook/blog that keeps track of your trips around the world and lets you share your journey in a super easy and convenient way. Nooooo, I do not get paid to write that. And even if I did I wouldn’t sell my soul to make a few bucks.</p>

<p>Anyway with that said, you can find our Polarsteps account here –&gt; Yachting Polarsteps and if you would like to keep track of us just download the app from the AppStore on your phone. 🙂</p>

<p>Below you’ll find our ongoing winter in Sicily.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="480" src="https://www.polarsteps.com/yachting/6409670-vinter-pa-sicilien/embed"></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Resa" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Well, let’s begin with the update… Since we (mainly Tony) are lazy, like crazy lazy, when it comes to writing an executive decision has been made in the social media department of Freya and that is that future blog posts will be written in Swedish instead of English. The main reason for that is that most of our “followers” (read friends and family) are Swedish and quite a few of them aren’t that savvy when it comes to reading and understanding English. However, we will still use English when we share stuff on Instagram, Facebook and other social media platforms aaaand the technical department will do its best to include some half-decent translation service for you. Sorry for any inconvenience but life isn’t fair. 😉]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/polarsteps.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/polarsteps.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kaptenen bakar</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/19/Kaptenen-bakar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kaptenen bakar" /><published>2023-01-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/19/Kaptenen-bakar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2023/01/19/Kaptenen-bakar.html"><![CDATA[<p>På sista tiden har kaptenen lagt sig till med en ny hobby, han har börjat baka både bröd och kakor med Herman här i skutan. Nu funderar ni som har lite bättre koll på oss såklart vem tusan Herman är, Herman är en liten burk fylld med surdegsgrund som numera har flyttat in i vår kyl. Det bästa Herman vet är när han matas med mjöl och vatten ett par gånger i veckan när det är bakdags.</p>

<p>Nu är det ju så att Herman är lite av en diva och måste matas minst en gång i veckan varken man bakar eller ej för att han inte ska tjura ihop, efter att han vuxit till sig får man antingen baka något gott, bröd, kakor, pannkakor, våfflor, kanel &amp; chokladbullar eller helt enkelt slänga överskottet. Då vi inte slänger mat på Freya har det därför blivit en hel del bakande på sista tiden.</p>

<p><img src="herman-1.jpg" /></p>
<center>Herman några timmar efter matning</center>

<p>I regel bakas det helt vanligt surdegsbröd (som är lite båtanpassat), brödet görs av Herman, mjöl, vatten, salt och lite socker så det är inte något vidare avancerat, receptet hittar du lite längre ner. Självklart går det peta i lite frön, oliver, tomat eller något annat gott för den som känner sig manad att spexa till det hela lite (se steg 6).</p>

<p><img src="surdegsbrod.jpg" /></p>
<center>Surdegsbröd direkt från ugnen</center>

<p>Om du känner suget av att baka bröd på samma sätt som på SY Freya så går det till såhär:</p>

<p>Först ser du till att ha följande hemma:</p>

<ul>
  <li>550 gram mjöl</li>
  <li>12 gram salt</li>
  <li>20 gram socker</li>
  <li>Fungerande vattenkran (de flesta hushåll har en)</li>
  <li>Surdegsbas, har du ingen så håll ett öga här på sidan så dyker det snart upp hur du gör en.</li>
</ul>

<p>1: På förmiddagen dagen innan du ska baka bröd matas ”Herman” med 50 gram vatten (1/2dl) och 50 gram (1dl) mjöl. Här på Freya använder vi vanligt vetemjöl men det sägs att det ska går bra med lite grövre mjöl också. Här får du prova dig fram om andan och lusten faller på.</p>

<p>Matningen görs så enkelt som det bara går, ös i mjöl och vatten i burken som Herman bor i och blanda det hela till en slät och fin smet. Efter 3-5 timmar i rumstemperatur (inte i solen) har Herman vuxit till sig och är ca 3 gånger så stor som vanligt (Herman gillar att bli matad och lägger på sig ganska fort).</p>

<p>2: När Herman har växt till sig så sleva över honom i en skål med 5 deciliter vatten där du löst upp 2 teskedar (10-12 gram) salt och 1 matsked (18-20 gram) socker, rör runt tills Herman är helt upplöst och vattnet ser ut som mjölk.</p>

<p>3: Blanda den numera upplösta Herman med 500gram mjöl och blanda runt ordentligt till en fin smet utan klumpar (här brukar jag köra med en helt vanlig slickepott). Det är kladdigt som tusan och kommer att sluta med att du har en klibbig/kladdig smet som är lite borderline till flytande. Det är helt och hållet i sin ordning. Degen jäser det inte några hysteriska mängder så om du har en skål som är minst dubbelt så stor som mjölet du öser i så bör det räcka fint.</p>

<p>4: Täck med en handduk och låt jäsa i ett par timmar vänd sedan runt smeten ordentligt, med den där slickepotten, och täck igen. Gör samma sak igen, runtvändandet av degen, fast en gång i timmen i ytterligare tre gånger medans degen jäser till sig och blir både större och mindre kladdig. Den kommer aldrig bli ”okladdig” så motstå frestelsen att ösa i mer mjöl för att göra degen fin och degig.</p>

<p><em>Här ska jag vara ärlig och säga att jag i regel hoppar över vändandet i alla fall så länge degen håller sig i bunken, det är ingen raketforskning så du hittar säkert ett bra sätt som passar dig.</em></p>

<p>5: Steg 5 är ett valfritt steg, här brukar jag blanda i lite av varje. Favoriten just nu är soltorkade tomater i olja som klipps i små bitar (mindre än 5mm i diameter) samtidigt som jag slår i ca 0.5 deciliter olivolja eller oljan som tomaterna ligger i. Vänd runt allt en hisklig massa så att det hela blandar sig fint i degen. Det går såklart fint med oliver, fetaost eller någon variant av fågelfrön som hittas på brödhyllorna i butikerna. Ta det som du gillar helt enkelt. Är det torra saker du stoppar i är det lättare att göra det innan steg 3.</p>

<p>6: Stoppa bunken i en plastpåse och ställ in i kylen och låt stå över natten.</p>

<p>7: På morgonen dag 2 klär du en brödform med bakplåtspapper och öser sedan i degen. Formen behöver vara i alla fall så stor så att den tillåter brödet att växa 50% (för dig som sov på matematiken i nian så betyder det behöver vara minst 2-3 cm kvar upp till kanten på en vanlig brödform) om du vill vara helt på den säkra sidan.</p>

<p>8: Här på Freya drivs ugnen på gas så det betyder att vi inte förvärmer den innan brödet åker in men sen i sin tur är ugnen stor som en skokartong så den blir varm ganska fort ändå. Vi sätter den på ca 180-200 grader och har brödet inne i 60 minuter. Om det börjar få lite för mycket färg på toppen lägger vi en bit aluminiumfolie över tills den där timmen gått.</p>

<p>9: Plocka ut brödet och låt svalna på galler för att få den där goa krispiga utsidan. När brödet svalnat kan du förvara det antingen insvept i en handduk eller i en plastpåse. Ta vad du har liggandes, om du har olja i brödet (se steg 6) så kan det ligga upp mot en vecka utan att bli torrt och tråkigt.</p>

<p>Knådigare än så gör vi det inte här ombord och gott blir det.</p>

<p>Så här såg sista baket ut.</p>

<p><img src="brod.jpg" /></p>
<center>Surdegsbröd med soltorkade tomater alá SY Freya</center>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Mat" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[På sista tiden har kaptenen lagt sig till med en ny hobby, han har börjat baka både bröd och kakor med Herman här i skutan. Nu funderar ni som har lite bättre koll på oss såklart vem tusan Herman är, Herman är en liten burk fylld med surdegsgrund som numera har flyttat in i vår kyl. Det bästa Herman vet är när han matas med mjöl och vatten ett par gånger i veckan när det är bakdags.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/herman-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/herman-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Weekend gas project</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2022/02/06/weekend-project-gas-solenoid-timer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weekend gas project" /><published>2022-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2022/02/06/weekend-project-gas-solenoid-timer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2022/02/06/weekend-project-gas-solenoid-timer.html"><![CDATA[<p>How many times have we forgotten to turn off the gas after cooking? The appropriate answer would be never but the honest one is almost every time. We cook, we eat, we do the dishes and hit the sofa. And right about that time, we look at each other and, “did you turn off the gas”? Crap… And it’s of course raining and it’s cold and it’s just not fun at all to climb out there to turn that nob.</p>

<p>The solution is of course to get one of those gas solenoids that allow you to close the gas remotely. Put one in the gas locker and connect it with a switch inside of the boat and you are good to go. Enable the gas with a flick of a finger without getting out. #perfect</p>

<p><img src="solenoid-1.jpg" /></p>

<p>The problem with those devices in my opinion is that you can still forget to turn them off and then the entire idea loses its point. So the grand master plan for the weekend was to build something cheap and foolproof. So the shopping spree ended with the following (yes I’m a sucker for AZ-Delivery even if they bumped their prices lately).</p>

<ul>
  <li>Solenoid from Amazon – 22€ – <a href="https://www.amazon.de/-/en/U-S-Solid-12-Solenoid-Valve/dp/B01NBUFFEG?pd_rd_w=RTdDW&amp;pf_rd_p=2e346047-29a4-42f6-a72d-de1e5e50b712&amp;pf_rd_r=JBS0C5Y5NGTWWXE7VSHW&amp;pd_rd_r=76d23c19-3add-419c-842e-7fdefab42f9e&amp;pd_rd_wg=InLsk&amp;pd_rd_i=B01NBUFFEG&amp;psc=1&amp;ref_=pd_bap_d_rp_1_t">Link</a></li>
  <li>Arduino Nano from AZ-Delivery – 7,50€ – <a href="https://www.az-delivery.de/en/products/nano-v3-0-pro">Link</a></li>
  <li>0,96″ OLED I2C Display from AZ – 4€ – <a href="https://www.az-delivery.de/en/collections/displays/products/0-96zolldisplay?variant=26462709385">Link</a></li>
  <li>DC-DC power supply step down module from AZ – 2,30€ – <a href="https://www.az-delivery.de/en/products/lm2596s-dc-dc-step-down-modul-1">Link</a></li>
  <li>Single-channel relay 5V from AZ – 2€ – <a href="https://www.az-delivery.de/en/products/relais-modul?variant=8138392076384">Link</a></li>
  <li>Box from Kjell&amp;Co – 0,5€ (got a pretty good deal on that one) – <a href="https://www.kjell.com/se/produkter/el-verktyg/elektronik/elektroniklador/ventilerad-inbyggnadslada-38x65-mm-p89041">Link</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I also got myself an MQ-2 Gas Sensor – 5€- Link – that will be added in version 2.0 of the switch.</p>

<p>Some quick and dirty code that display if the solenoid is open or closed and the countdown till it’s closed if we “buy” time by pressing the small button. For those of you, that understands geek you’ll soon find some useless lines below with a small “easter egg”. Without those, the code can be cut in half.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>#include &lt;Wire.h&gt;
#include &lt;Adafruit_GFX.h&gt;
#include &lt;Adafruit_SSD1306.h&gt;

#define SCREEN_WIDTH 128
#define SCREEN_HEIGHT 64

Adafruit_SSD1306 display(SCREEN_WIDTH, SCREEN_HEIGHT, &amp;Wire, -1);

  const int RELAY_PIN = 2;
  const int BUTTON_PIN = 3;

  int buttonState = NULL;
  int lastState = NULL;
  int mc = 0;
void setup() {
  pinMode(RELAY_PIN, OUTPUT);
  pinMode(BUTTON_PIN, INPUT);
  Serial.begin(115200);

  if(!display.begin(SSD1306_SWITCHCAPVCC, 0x3C)) {
    for(;;);
  }
  delay(2000);

}
void time2goM(int tid2go,int s)
{
  display.clearDisplay();
  display.setTextSize(2);
  display.setTextColor(WHITE);

  display.setCursor(37, 3);
  display.print("Timer");
  display.drawLine(30, 19, 100, 19, WHITE);

  display.setTextSize(4);
  if (tid2go&lt;100 &amp;&amp; tid2go&gt;9) {
      display.setCursor(40, 30);
    } else {
      display.setCursor(57, 30);
    }
      
  display.print(tid2go);

  display.setTextSize(2);
  display.setCursor(95,43);
  display.print(s);

  display.display();
}

void time2goS(int tid2go)
{
  display.clearDisplay();
  display.setTextSize(2);
  display.setTextColor(WHITE);

  display.setCursor(37, 3);
  display.drawLine(30, 19, 100, 19, WHITE);
  display.print("Timer");

  display.setTextSize(4);
  if(tid2go&gt;9) {
      display.setCursor(45, 30);
    } else {
      display.setCursor(55, 30);
    }
  display.print(tid2go);

  display.display();
}

void maxTime(int mc) {
  display.clearDisplay();
  display.setTextColor(WHITE);
  
  if(mc&lt;3) {
  display.drawRect(4, 4, display.width()-4, display.height()-4, WHITE);
  display.drawRect(8, 8, 115, 52, WHITE);
  display.setTextSize(2);
  display.setCursor(20, 16);
  display.print("Max time");
  display.setCursor(27, 36);
  display.print("60 min!");
  display.display();
  delay(1500);
  } else if (mc&gt;2 &amp;&amp; mc&lt;5){
  display.setTextSize(1);
  display.setCursor(1, 1);
  display.write("Hey I said max 60 minIs it really that hard to understand how this thingie works? Is it? Really? Really? I probably going to break myself if you continue clicking!");
  display.display();
  delay(5000);
  } else {
  display.setTextSize(2);
  display.setCursor(10, 1);
  display.write("Screw you! I'm going home!");
  display.display();
  delay(50000);
  }
  }

void endTime() {
  display.clearDisplay();
  display.drawRect(4, 4, display.width()-4, display.height()-4, WHITE);
  display.drawRect(8, 8, 115, 52, WHITE);
  display.setTextSize(2);
  display.setTextColor(WHITE);
  display.setCursor(45, 15);
  display.print("Gas");
  display.setCursor(25, 35);
  display.print("Closed!");
  display.display(); 
  }

void loop() {
buttonState = digitalRead(BUTTON_PIN);

if(buttonState == HIGH &amp;&amp; lastState == LOW) {
            
  lastState = buttonState;

  for(int m = 14; m &gt; -1; m--) {
    for (int s = 59; s &gt;= 0; s--) {
      delay(1000);
      digitalWrite(RELAY_PIN, HIGH);
          
      buttonState = digitalRead(BUTTON_PIN);
      
      if(buttonState == HIGH &amp;&amp; lastState == LOW) {
        m += 15;
        if(m&gt;59){
          mc += 1;
          m = 59;
          maxTime(mc);
          }
      }
      
      lastState = buttonState;
        
      if(m&lt;1) {
        time2goS(s);

      } else {
        time2goM(m,s);
      }
    }
  }
}
  digitalWrite(RELAY_PIN, LOW);
  endTime();  
}
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Since I’m not a super geek it took some trial and error to get everything up and running so about 18 cups of coffee later the timer was ready and did what it was supposed to.</p>

<p><img src="gasBoard-1024x1024.jpg" /></p>

<p>Besides connecting the button to pin D3 and the relay to pin D2 the display got connected according to its specifications. The 10K ohm pull-down resistor to the ground takes care of strange behaviour (erratic on/off) from the floating input.</p>

<p>When the setup was tested the only thing that was left was to solder the components together and squeeze everything into the, a bit too small, box.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="solder-2048x1536.jpg" /></td>
      <td><img src="box.jpg" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Surprisingly everything worked just fine with no short circuits even after the lid was in place. 🙂</p>

<p>Some takeaways from the project, use a bigger box or make the device decentralised to save space.</p>

<p>Version 2.0 will have a slightly bigger box and a gas detector that will close the solenoid if gas is detected where it’s not supposed to be.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ytOiE5R33U0?si=bf2MndypCW1c6r_g" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Fix" /><category term="Freya" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How many times have we forgotten to turn off the gas after cooking? The appropriate answer would be never but the honest one is almost every time. We cook, we eat, we do the dishes and hit the sofa. And right about that time, we look at each other and, “did you turn off the gas”? Crap… And it’s of course raining and it’s cold and it’s just not fun at all to climb out there to turn that nob.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/solenoid-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/solenoid-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What the heck happened with Trull and Co during 2021</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/12/24/What-happened.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What the heck happened with Trull and Co during 2021" /><published>2021-12-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-12-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/12/24/What-happened</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/12/24/What-happened.html"><![CDATA[<p>What the heck happened with Trull and Co during 2021?</p>

<p>Well, that’s a darn good question, Trull and her crew just disappeared in thin air, or at least from https://yachting.earth. Not a word, no nothing except some strange sunny posts on <a href="https://instagram.com/yachting.earth">Instagram</a> from another country and boat than Trull (if you follow us there).</p>

<p>As you already might have guessed there has been a ton of changes during the last year and this is our attempt to somehow get back on track.</p>

<p>Anyway, once upon a time…<br />
Everything started with Tony’s father, when we reached the North Sea after the Kiel canal, dropping him a text with a link to a 50 foot something steel Colin Archer that was up for sale. He explained that when we reach the Mediterranean he wasn’t interested in sailing his old small boat, he wanted to sail something new and bigger and this Colin Archer was for sure a “slightly” bigger boat than Trull so he thought it would be a nice upgrade for him, I mean us…</p>

<p>Needless to say, we didn’t buy the CA but that didn’t stop Tony’s father to keep sending ads to other boats and about 500 ads later when we reached northern Spain and Gijon one of the boats spoke to us. We found Freya a Swedish Malö 116 located in Greece. Unfortunately, we had a small problem seeing her due to Covid so after an obscene amount of emails with her current owner we decided to kill the piggy bank and make a down payment. After that it was more or less downhill, we just had to set sail and sneak across the border into Portugal, back to Spain through Orca (killer whale) infested waters, through the Mediterranean, around Italy and up to Greece in a few months during the lockdown. How hard could it be? 🙂</p>

<p>The interesting part of the story was that it wasn’t that hard at all, we left Gijon in February heading to la Coruna and further south still during lockdown but apparently that didn’t apply to foreign boats. It’s about here we lost contact with the world, mostly because we sailed a lot from anchorage to anchorage and bounced in and out of marinas while trying to figure out how to get to Greece and our new boat and not least what to do with our beloved Trull that was up for sale at the moment. What would we do if someone bought her right there and then? Long story a lot shorter, eventually we ended up in Portimão, southern Portugal, where we stopped and tried to figure out our next move. Since both Italy and Greece was under some sort of super Covid lockdown so we didn’t want to take any chances and sail there and try to get into the country, after all, sailing a few weeks straight and having to turn around wasn’t our cup of tea so we ended up staying in Portimão for about 6 weeks till Greece reopened their borders.</p>

<p>During that time we found a buyer of Trull, a Swede and a Russian guy who lived in Portugal had been trying to find a nice looking B31 in Sweden for a few years to buy and sail down to Portugal and Portimão. I don’t think I have to say that the transaction went like a charm, they looked at Trull on day 1, day 2 we got the down payment of 50% and on day 3 they paid the rest. We stayed on the boat for another 3 weeks till we left for Greece and Freya.</p>

<p>Freya’s home at the time was Ionian Marina just 5 minutes by car from Preveza airport so the trip was super easy besides that we first had to go to Schiphol from Faro before we could get on our flight to Preveza. Usually, this wouldn’t be a major problem but this time we had about 90kg of extra luggage with us, you know the most important things, toothbrush, passport, life jackets, VHF, some “don’t leave home without them”-tools and some other of our can’t live or sail without it stuff, that we had to run between our gates with.</p>

<p>We were lucky enough that one of our friends had his boat in the Ionian marina that we could stay on instead of finding a hotel. We were even luckier when we found out that our friends’ boat was located next to Freya. What are the odds of that on a yard with thousands of boats?</p>

<p>When we met Freya that late June evening the first thing that struck us was how big she was compared to Trull. Not big big but crazy super big! (boats usually looks way bigger than they are from underneath when they are on dry land ).</p>

<p>The next few days were spent talking with Joachim and Birgitte, her current owners, having a surveyor checking her out and reviewing some of the findings (more about that later) and last but not least giving her an extra layer of coating before launching. It was for sure a few busy, and super crazy hot, days before she was ready to go back into the water where she belongs.</p>

<iframe title="Bottom coating" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9iBM4NK3gwI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>If it only went that fast…</em></p>

<p>When she finally got off the hard we had a beautiful test sail in true Ionian summer spirit. We spent the day in the light, warm and super nice winds outside of Preveza before we dropped off and waved goodbye to Joachim and Birgitte and took aim at our anchorage for our first night on Freya. The next few weeks were spent digging through the boat to clean out everything we didn’t need and at the same time learn as much about her as we possibly could to create a project plan of all the things that needs to be done within the next year.</p>

<p>The summer was then spent investigating nice anchorages, cute towns, great restaurants and of course coffee shops and bars across the west coast of Greece from Corfu in the north to Kefalonia in the south.</p>

<p><img src="Yachting/blog/2021-12-24-What-happened/map.png" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Western Greece</i></center>

<p>During our ~walk-about~ sail-about this summer we found quite a lot of gems in the area, some of our Ionian favourite spots are;</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Café di Paris (Lefkas/Nidri), great place in Nidri if you are up for a cocktail or two, they’ve got stunning waffles, pizza, burger etc. We spent an obscene amount of time there during the summer. If you go there say hi to Panos (the owner) from us.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Θεα Cafe Bar (Lefkas/Nidri), small and sweet coffee place with an amazing view. About 40 minutes by foot from Nidri but well worth the time and the steps. Their pancakes are to die for even if they are a biiiit expensive.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="pancake-1024x1000.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Sometimes pancakes are the only thing you need</i></center>

<ul>
  <li>Midsummer bay, this is the place where Swedes, us included, spend their Midsummer if they are in the area. Calm bay with no cellular reception what so ever, the only thing there is to do is chilling and enjoying life. The bay next door has got two small restaurants, aim for the on the right that’s the best one. They also sell ice for your cocktails.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="midsommar-1024x1018.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Midsummer with newfound friends, the crew from Freya, BaraVara and Columbina</i></center>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Stavros Pontoon (Sivota/Lefkas). Super friendly and helpful staff and a nice and cozy restaurant with a view over the “marina”, we might have spent a few to many evenings here. Great place to recharge both yourself and the boat, it’s free to stay at their pontoon if you dine at the restaurant, water, shower and electricity is included.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Palairos Yacht Club (Palarios/mainland), okey this is the place to go if you are into ekmek cake. Sweet Jesus they know how to make this delicious cake variant of bread pudding from heaven or more accurately from Turkey. Moore next to the beach, jump into the dinghy and beach it just next to the Yacht Club. The amazing sunset is included in the price.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="ekmek-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Ekmek cake at Palairos Yacht Club</i></center>

<p><img src="palarios-sunset-1024x768.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Sunset at Palairos Yacht Club</i></center>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Panorama, indian restaurant (Palarios/mainland), if you still are up for food after your ekmek cake then Panorama is the place to aim for. It’s the place with the green sunshades. We and a, eumm, few friends (17 of us) dropped by and had dinner and not one of us was dissatisfied with the food. Go there, eat a lot of food and be happy that you didn’t pick the place next door.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pera Pigadi, super clear water and a great stopover either at the quay or at anchor. Great place for snorkelling with lots and lots of fish to enjoy.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<iframe title="Pera Pigadi" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wRAn3qsWJI0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Corfu town. If you are into strolling around among turists and shop for ugly t-shirts with “I &lt;3 Greece” on the chest this is the place, oooooor if you drag yourself to the outskirts of the old town where you find great coffee shops and nice bars. Totally worth a visit. Drop your anchor in the bay next to the fort and you are good to go.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Just south of Corfu you’ll find two small island Paxos and Antipaxos, when we dropped by the bay was empty and it felt like we had the entire island for ourselves.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="antipaxos-1-1024x729.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Antipaxos</i></center>

<p>Besides the places above we’ve visited a ton of other great places, the entire Ionian is jam-packed with them. The only thing you need is a lot of time or a lot of diesel since you can’t really rely on the wind in the area. Sometimes there’s a lovely 30 knots breeze perfect for sailing and the other minute there’s nothing. But since the only thing we have an unlimited supply of is time we didn’t mind cruising around here at all. 🙂</p>

<p><img src="sailing-1024x768.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Rebecka at the helm, Poseidon keep your head down!! 🙂</i></center>

<p>When the summer was about to end our grand master plan was to sail west back to Spain and hook up with some friends that we met on our way south from Sweden but the circumstances (other friends and crappy weather) made us decide to stay in Greece for some time so we ended up in Messolongi, a small town on the mainland that doesn’t need tourism to survive which means that everything is a lot cheaper than the “regular” tourist places and best of all, nothing closes down during winter. More or less everything can be found in the area so it’s a perfect place to stay to finalise some of those boat projects that are still pending…</p>

<p>So now you know what the heck happened. 🙂</p>

<p><img src="freya-top.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<center><i>Freya from above</i></center>]]></content><author><name>Tony Johansson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Grekland" /><category term="Freya" /><category term="Trull" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What the heck happened with Trull and Co during 2021?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/antipaxos-1-1024x729.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/antipaxos-1-1024x729.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">a Coruna to Camarinas</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/04/13/a-coruna-to-camarinas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a Coruna to Camarinas" /><published>2021-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/04/13/a-coruna-to-camarinas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/04/13/a-coruna-to-camarinas.html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="aCoruna-1024x768.jpg"></a></p>

<p>We left the marina in A Coruña at dawn and the other two Swedish boats, Beyond and Corsico, left at the same time. There are two marinas next to each other in A Coruña and we were not in the same marina. The only way to see that the other two boats were on their way out at the same time was by looking at the AIS. There was a dense fog so we couldn’t see each other until we got really close. For us that dense fog was a new experience but we had been warned about fog in the Spanish rias and along the Portuguese coast. Because of that we bought a fog horn the other day. We had a can with pressurized air and a horn on it but if there is a lot of fog to come we didn’t want to risk using up the can so now we also have a manual fog horn that you blow in. Thankfully on this occasion the fog cleared up quite quickly and gave us a beautiful sunrise instead.</p>

<p><a href="fog-sunrise-1536x1152.jpg"></a></p>

<p>The trip to Camariñas started out with almost no wind for the first few hours and then the wind picked up a bit and we got good speed and for the last few nautical miles we had a beam reach with gusts up to 14 m/s, that was quite intense but it worked out well. Our average speed for the day was 5 knots which is fast for us but compared to Beyond and Corisco we were still quite slow. We saw them getting further and further ahead of us becoming smaller and smaller dots in the horizon until we couldn’t see them at all. When we approached the marina in Camariñas both Corisco and Beyond were anchored in the bay outside the marina. According to the weather forecast the wind was going to be quite strong the coming days so we decided to go into the marina. About an hour or so after our arrival Beyond called and asked about the conditions in the marina and a short while later they joined us. Mia cooked red curry chicken with rice and we all had dinner and a really nice evening together.</p>

<p>The next day was spent walking around in the village, we found some funny little stone houses on pillars in almost every garden we walked by. After some research we found out that they are called hórreos and that they are used for storing grain or other food. They stand on pillars with a slightly rounded stones on top to keep rodents out and the houses have slits in their walls to make sure the ventilation is good.</p>

<p><a href="house-1536x1152.jpg"></a></p>

<p>We have mentioned before that since we came to Spain we have had almost no wind or too much wind and we don’t want to sail when it’s too much wind. But when Karin and Richard on Beyond said that they were probably leaving the next day we got inspired. When we arrived to Camariñas and looked at the weather forecast we expected to have to stay here for up to a week before the weather calmed down enough for us to move on. But we had a good look at the forecast and talked a bit about it and the wind was going to be north easterly which meant from behind us most of the time and the average wind between 8-10 m/s and gust up to 15 m/s. It’s a huge difference going down wind or broad reaching with winds of 8-15 m/s compared to beating against the wind. We ended up deciding that is was a good idea for us to leave the next day as well. We had paid for three nights when we arrived but we managed to explain to the nice lady in the office that didn’t speak English that we were leaving a day early and it was no problem to get the money back for the third night. We went to bed early looking forward to some good sailing and a nice day in the sun the next day.</p>]]></content><author><name>Mia Larsson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Spanien" /><category term="Trull" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/aCoruna-1024x768.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/aCoruna-1024x768.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Camariñas to Muros</title><link href="https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/03/17/Camarinnas-to-Muros.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Camariñas to Muros" /><published>2021-03-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/03/17/Camarinnas-to-Muros</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yachting.earth/segling/2021/03/17/Camarinnas-to-Muros.html"><![CDATA[<p>We left marina Camariñas under a lot calmer conditions than we expected looking at the weather forecast the night before. Of course you want enough wind to be able to sail but it can be magical when you motor out of a marina at dawn and everything around is just calm and quiet and you can watch the sun rise and the day wake up. This particular morning was even more magical since we were followed by a pod of dolphins. They joined us just outside of the marina and followed us almost all the way out to the open sea.</p>

<p><img src="sunset.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>It’s difficult with the weather forecasts in this area since you have to take the effect of the mountains and the rias into account as well and we haven’t quite figured that out completely yet. And sometimes of course the forecast is just wrong. We had expected a lot more wind than we got in the beginning of the day. Beyond left Carmariñas a short while after us and we kept in contact over the VHF during the day. They decided to go a bit further off shore to try to find some more wind but we stayed closer to shore and eventually the wind picked up enough to turn the engine off and get some good sailing. The sun was out all day and it was really warm and we had to peal off some of our layers of clothing. Tony even changed to his shorts. The last 4-5 nm approaching the marina got a bit chilly since we had to beat against the wind to get there. That is something that I (Mia) still need to get used to, being so close to the goal but having to spend hours to get there. It’s a natural part of the everyday life of sailing but when we get that close to a marina I get restless and just want to get there as fast as possible.</p>

<p><img src="Yachting/blog/2021-03-17-Camarinnas-to-Muros/map.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Camariñas to Muros</p>

<p>The marina in Muros is nice and calm and Pedro that runs the marina is a bit of a character in a positive way. He seems to really like his job. One big plus is the showers, for once it’s not “push button” showers, they have normal taps and you can adjust the temperature and the pressure as you like. Muros is a cute little village that you can “do” in a day or two<sup>*</sup>. (* Note from Tony: More like 25 minutes….)</p>

<p>After two nights in Muros Karin and Richard on Beyond left for Ria de Vigo and an anchorage there. Our plan was to leave the same morning but we didn’t sleep very well during the night and it felt like it was a bit too windy for us. We got reports from Beyond during the day and for a while they had gust up to 18 m/s. The sea was still quite calm which makes it a bit easier but we were happy with our decision to stay in the marina.</p>

<p>We have been talking back and forth about whether to stick around and explore the different rias in Galicia for a while or if we should keep going south as soon as possible. On the one hand we want to get as far south as possible and into the Mediterranean as soon as possible since we got a signed contract on our “new” boat that we are picking up in Greece. Because of that we are of course eager to get to Greece. But on the other hand Greece is in lock down due to the situation with COVID-19 and according to the latest news their plan is to open up again on the 14th of May. We could get to Portugal in a few days but Portugal has a lot more restrictions due to COVID-19 than Spain, for an example they have a curfew from 1 pm on the weekend. But we don’t really have a problem being confined to the boat in the afternoons on the weekend. If we want to walk around and explore things we can do that on weekdays. That’s the beauty with our new lifestyle. To be honest it feels like we are slowly but surely getting closer to a decision to keep heading south without unnecessary detours.</p>]]></content><author><name>Mia Larsson</name></author><category term="Segling" /><category term="Spanien" /><category term="Trull" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We left marina Camariñas under a lot calmer conditions than we expected looking at the weather forecast the night before. Of course you want enough wind to be able to sail but it can be magical when you motor out of a marina at dawn and everything around is just calm and quiet and you can watch the sun rise and the day wake up. This particular morning was even more magical since we were followed by a pod of dolphins. They joined us just outside of the marina and followed us almost all the way out to the open sea.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://yachting.earth/map.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://yachting.earth/map.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>